It was probably the craziest promotion
I've ever experienced.
>> This is David Fowler. He got promoted 11
times from an intern to a distinguished
engineer, all at Microsoft. And I asked
him about everything he learned along
the way.
>> A lot of things that get you to senior
and maybe principal hurt you growing
even further.
>> What are the hidden unexpected perks of
getting promoted to a distinguished
engineer? Okay, the coolest part. Also,
since he's been at Microsoft for over 17
years, I asked him for his unique
perspectives about the company. Did you
notice anything internally when Satia
became CEO?
>> The culture just changed completely.
Right.
>> Before you change roles, ask when the
last reorg was. What's the thinking
behind that advice? I'm curious what has
kept you at Microsoft as long as you've
been.
Here's the full episode.
First thing I wanted to go over is I
think Microsoft's leveling system is a
little bit unique compared to the other
big tech companies. I see on levels.fy
that the leveling system goes from 59 to
70 and there's almost two levels per
uh title, you know, two levels per SD1,
two levels for SD2, two in senior and it
keeps going on all the way down to
distinguished. Can you explain the
Microsoft leveling system a little bit?
>> Yeah. So, I I can't tell you why it
starts at 59. I'm sure someone who's
been there longer than me can tell you
why it starts at 59. I believe there
levels below that that aren't
engineering roles and that's probably
why it it has that system. Um, so when
you join from college, you typically
start at 59 or 60 depending on like how
many how many times you intern, how well
you did. There's different things that
go into it. Um but entry is 59. So
that's like sweet one at other
companies. Um and then you you progress
in level in Microsoft there are things
called level bands. So then you say
there's like two levels per title. The
title tends to be the band. Um so you
can say like I I am a junior engineer.
You could be 59 or 60. So you can't you
can't tell from someone's title which
which notch they're at. Um so there's
you know 59 60 is sweet one 50 61 62 is
two and then 64 is um senior and then
principal is actually three levels. I
never really sat and thought about the
why is it's done that way. I'm sure
people that are really smart came up
with those levels and why they're that
that way. But the like principal level
the the the band is so broad the depth
of experience of the people in that band
is immense. So you could be talking to
someone who is like the last level of
principal band that's been there forever
or someone who just entered the
principal band that just came from
senior um and you wouldn't know from
looking at their title. stuff and then
beyond that is like no one knows right
it's like levels partner um that has
three bands and then there's beyond
partners like technical fellow and sales
engineer yep so yeah it's a it's a broad
system you know
>> yeah thanks for laying that out so yeah
that's the thing I want to dig into is I
mean you went through this entire thing
you started all the way as an intern
>> and you've been there for your entire
career and you grew all the way to
distinguished
>> um so I kind of want to go over that
story. Could you tell me the story
behind you joining Microsoft?
>> Yeah. So, I went to college at Florida
Tech and I'm from Barbados. I left
Barbados at like 18 like like everyone
else that goes to college. Went to
college. Funny enough, I was looking for
colleges that had career fairs and I
chose one that was closest to like our
business. It's one flight home to the
Caribbean from Florida. So, that was a
really convenient place I got in. Um,
funny enough, my first major was
computer engineering cuz I thought I
wanted to do software and hardware, but
in the first class I was like, nope, not
for me. I want to code. I have been
coding since I was like 10 years old.
So, that that's what I want to do. Um,
changed majors to computer science, did
my first year of programming. I thought,
funny enough, I thought people that
chose computer science had been doing
programming like their whole life and
they knew what they wanted to do. But in
the first Java class, like no one knew
how to code. I was like, this is kind of
crazy. I thought I thought this was like
a thing everyone that chose computer
science would do before you come here.
And that was kind of like being tossed
into the pit of computer science, like
learning about algorithms. And then
after that, I kind of met one of my one
of my my best friends. Um to this day,
still we still best friends. And we
started to make games.
And we have been working on like nights
and weekends making games for fun at
school. And we by the time the first
career fair came around, there were a
bunch of companies that came in to kind
of you know see see different students
and we thought to ourselves how do we
differentiate from other students. So we
came in with a laptop showing our game
demo and we we showed us all all the
recruiters. Um and that first year we
got like a I think like four offers for
internships. I got Microsoft, GE, a
bunch of other small smaller companies
in Florida and my friend went to EA. So
he had we built a game, he went to EA,
you know, interviewed there, got
interned there. I went to Microsoft. Um,
and that's how I got the internship. Um,
I showed him the game. We I did
interviews on campus, flew out, did
full-time interviews, you know, before
COVID where it was all inerson
whiteboarding. Uh, got my internship and
that was kind of like history. Um I
interned twice
uh 2006 and seven. It it was eye
opening. It's coming from a small
country going to a big company
experiencing like big campus big
technology um talking to people who were
like really really really smart
absorbing information. It was it was
kind of it was great. Um and I was part
of the last set of set of interns that
got to go to Bill House. That was kind
of that was kind of fun.
What what was that like going to Bill
Gates's house?
>> So, historically, every intern group at
the end of the summer got to go to Bill
Gates house. That that was the the main
event, right? Um, in my time at least,
and you would get picked up in a bus and
they would take all your technology.
They would take away your phones, take
all your stuff, give you instructions.
You actually park out, I think, at a
church and they would take your stuff so
you could take pictures. you get, you
know, they would tell you like what you
can and can't do at the house and then
all the interns were just going to his
his like big really huge mansion.
Um, funny story is I recall just
standing around talking to interns, not
paying attention to what was happening
and I remember seeing a rush of interns
like run towards me and I couldn't
figure what was going on. I turned
around. He was like, he was behind me
like
there's Bill Gates. I shook his hand.
So, you see I I spoke to him once.
>> When you interviewed for Microsoft at
the time in 2006,
was there leak code or what what did the
process look like at the time? What kind
of things did they ask?
>> There's a book called um how would you
move Mount Fuji? And it's this classic
book um doing tech interviews like
Microsoft created these like le code
style um puzzles that everyone loved to
hate. Now like the puzzles that are like
why is a manual cover round is one of
the most famous ones that people would
ask you a question.
>> Okay.
>> When I when I was on campus doing the um
interview I'll never forget they they
were asking me questions and I had been
prepped for coding coding interviews. I
had been thinking about like coding
stuff but I hadn't taken all the classes
yet because I I was in my first year of
of university so I hadn't done like all
the courses required to learn about all
the things right so it was me on my own
my friend trying to figure out how to
like what how to prep for interviews and
they asked me it's so it's so visceral
they asked me a piling drum question
super easy not not hard I did it on
paper like with a pencil like writing on
paper and then they asked me did you
ever watch Die Hard 3?
>> No.
>> There's a scene where Bruce Willis and
Sam Jackson have to stop a bomb from
from going off and there's like water on
a f in a fountain and they have um a
five gallon jug and a three a three
gallon jug and they have to make exactly
four gallons to avoid the the the
disaster.
>> Oh, okay. Okay.
>> And I had seen the movie, right? But I
couldn't remember the secrets of steps
required to get that to work. And in an
interview my my after the coding
question they asked this this puzzle,
right? So you have infinite water and
you you want to make four gallons and
you have a three and a five jug and you
have to make exactly four gallons. Like
how do you do it? And I sat there and I
was like oh my god this is that hard and
I I figured out but it was it was funny
because it to me it was like this is
like pre-le code not even thinking about
solving some sorting question or
something. This is just like puzzles
like can you think through puzzles? Um,
and the last question was, "How do you
count the number of gas stations in
Florida?" And I sat there and I was
like, "Is this a trick question?" And
the guy listened to me. He says, "No."
And I'm like, "What? I don't get the
point. I don't get the point of this
stuff." And I thought I had I thought I
had like done really poorly, but they
had they called me, so I was like,
"Okay, I could have failed miserably."
That's so funny because people hate on
leak code all the time, but these
puzzles, it sounds like leak code's
better than these puzzles. Actually,
it's related to the job.
>> I don't even know if you can prepare for
some of these things. Like my my last
interview, my my second last interview
when I was when I flew out and was on
campus, I got asked how do I add two
numbers in base -2? That was my final
question. It was just like
>> what?
>> It's come a long way since then.
>> It's this changed a lot. I mean like
some for the better, some for the worse.
>> So going back to the story then. Um so
after you had the internships I you
committed for full-time
>> and then you had a pretty quick career
growth on the outset and I see that
there are a few pivotal projects that
led to the upward trajectory past
senior. Kind of want to talk about the
story behind those projects. So for
instance, maybe we can start with NuGet
which is the package manager. What's the
story behind that project?
>> That was interesting because NuGet I
think we're like 10 plus years in now is
like the the package manager fornet it
was when I think think about the impact
now compared to what it was when it
started. It's kind of jarring because we
started off we were building a brand new
web stack and we were trying to compete
with like the LAMP stack right so LAMP
was like Linux Apache my SQL PHP and we
were competing with that from a net
windows server standpoint whether or not
that made sense or not at the time I
didn't I didn't think about that stuff
like the bosses above me told me we're
doing that like let's do it so we built
this whole this whole new web stack and
Ruby on Rails
had come out like concurrently at the
same time and gems was like this huge
deal. Ruby gems, get gems, get packages,
you know, run commands in Rails. And we
had seen that, but there was also a
cohort in the company looking at things
like WordPress and Drupal and those have
packages too. And I think the consensus
was we need to have an a package manager
to like pull in packages so you can
extend the platform. And the very first
version of Nougat was this in browser
package manager that was like a
WordPress thing. And I remember we had
this meeting with um who is now an EVP,
Scott Guthrie, and it was all about like
reals and gems and we have to compete
with the package manager and there was a
product manager who had mocked up in
screenshots and PowerPoint an experience
and it was me working with an architect
saying like we had built something like
can we just take start from here and
that that that meeting formed the the
Nougat team. It was me. I was the first
engineer. There was an architect um
David Evo and Phil Hack and we we were
the the founding team of of Nougat.
There were other open source nent
package managers in the ecosystem open
rack and and new and we like had a
conversation with some of some of those
those people and we started off this
mission to to build a package manager
for this fornet. And so when you were
building this, it sounds like it got
pretty uh critical adoption within the
net platform.
>> Yeah.
>> What did your performance review look
like when you were you finished building
this thing? Was that like a really
incredible success for someone who
wasn't even a senior engineer yet?
>> Yeah, I got my first promotion came like
eight months in when I when I when I
joined um even before Nougat. I think
like my first year was me I I had
interned twice so I had a lot of
experience like with just Microsoft just
in general and I would work on the
things I I was assigned and then I work
on more stuff. One of the things I did
was I would troll forums looking for
feedback for our products and I would
just build features to to solve them.
And I just did that over and over and
over and then kind of showed product
managers and the team and architects and
who turns out were my sponsors um I
guess in in the looking back on on how
it how it went. And I think that helped
me be in a place where I could be the
one to build Nougat. I would I would
basically just look for problems to
solve and I would attempt to code them
first. I was very I mean maybe I'm still
the same way. I'm a code first, ask
questions later kind of person. So my my
whole thing is code is currency. I can
show you a working sample. It's not a
PowerPoint. It's not a document. Here's
a working example of something. Oh, we
should start there and then move on to
something else. Um, so my review for
Nugette was like I I was getting really
good reviews early in my career because
I would I would just grab things.
Funnily enough, one of my directors at
the time told me like maybe five years
ago that he would just tell people that
David has energy. Go talk to him. Maybe
that's why stuff stuff came my way.
You mentioned that NG get grew way past
your what you imagined and I know at
some companies there's this idea of
deferred impact where sometimes people
continue to get credit for something
that they built and is continuing to pay
out for the company. Did you see
anything like that in your subsequent
performance reviews? Yeah, I I want to
say maybe the bigger ones the bigger
ones felt to me like a conglomeration of
history like past success adding up plus
success. Um I think at Microsoft in in
general impact is supposed to be for the
year but I think when you're doing these
I think there sometimes we call them
band changes right so when you jump
across bands it's a bigger promotion
within band is a smaller promotion so if
I go from you know 61 to 62 I'm still
but you know it's still worth a
promotion but when you jump when you
cross the boundary of going from two to
senior or senior principal
you require more more things to to more
impact to to make that that leap. And I
think I'm not sure if there's an
official deferred impact um
thing in Microsoft, but I I remember
that did come into play when I when I
went to, you know, higher levels of
principle and and stuff because it was
it was definitely not a one-off like,
oh, you you did this one thing this year
or like you're promoted. It's like h
have you been showing repeated impact
over the last 10 years and do we want to
you know keep you going forward etc etc.
So I think it did it did matter.
>> You mentioned some other larger
projects. So um maybe we can talk about
some of those. So there was a signal
signal or is it signal?
>> Signal R. Yeah. So that okay that that
came from that the naming the naming is
the time frame came from the time of
flicker web 2.0 remove ease from the end
of things. That's I don't know why we
called it signer. I mean we know why but
that was a fun project. I had been
working on nights and weekends on this
project and it was funnily enough like
Google Docs came out and I have been
like enthralled with the fact that you
could co-edit in a document. I was like
this is just nuts and it works super
well concurrently and I was like can we
do this for code? So I had to start I I
went off trying to build Google docs for
code could have been rich but ah didn't
do that anyway and while doing it I
learned about websockets which actually
hadn't come out yet. I learned about
basically how to build those kinds of
apps and that led to the creation of
signal R. In the meantime there was a
product manager on the team Damon
Edwards who was also building a talk to
describe how to build long running
streaming apps innet. So I had seen his
talk and I was like hey I'm building
this thing we should collaborate on this
new library right so that kind of
spawned the like night side weekends
what we call Microsoft you can moonlight
and work on things that are not tied to
your work um separately officially. So
we had been doing that like overnight we
just work on this things up until
midnight every night. Um, we made it
open source and then people started to
use it and we were like, okay, this is
interesting. It's catching catching on
becoming a thing now. It was still just
two of us working on this every now and
then. Didn't know what we were doing
really kind of like just building this
thing to make it work. And then at some
point a product manager at Microsoft on
the team said, "Hey, we should make this
official."
And that's when that I think that was
the first thing I experienced like
building a project from scratch.
Previously I had been working on other
people's ideas. You know someone had a
great idea. I was a a decent dev. I
would come in and be like found
engineer. This one was like my
brainchild. So it was very much I we
built the proto. I built the entire
thing from scratch and now I was being
given the chance to have a have a team
to work on it. Um, I was never a
manager, but I was the pseudo tech lead.
So, we we hired like kids from college
that ended up working on Signalar. I had
we had a team of like eight, I think, at
one point. And it was surreal because it
was like, okay, there is this random
thing that I built like on a weekend and
then it kind of turning into this
project that's real.
>> What was the motivation for SignalR?
What made you pull the weekends and the
late nights to build this thing that
seems like it was outside of Microsoft?
>> I hadn't seen anything like it. Like
when when Google Docs came out, it was
first of its kind to work that well
and it just felt super new and no one I
hadn't seen apps do that and it was like
how do we enable more apps to do the
same kind of thing. Node.js JS like
socket io and node were super new and
socket io had just come out and it was
like oh that's a really cool way of
building these apps that are that are
chat and and can send stuff from server
to client and we just I think that just
drove me because it was like okay I
hadn't I hadn't seen people attempt to
do this before let's just let's push
it's funny we we pushed the boundaries
of like the technology a bit we had
limits like all over the place in in the
tech stack that became problems to solve
deep in the deep in the core platform
too. So that that was a really good um
way to learn learn more about the
overall networking stack. And I think
the the the amount of problems we got to
tackle maybe made it enthralling for
like a a dev that like I got nurse
night. It was like catnip.
>> I was like, "Oh my god,
>> that this is so interesting because you
grew through this project and it was
permissionless, which is that no one
handed it to you. There wasn't some
manager, some PM that came to you and
said, "Hey, your staff's on this
project. You just went and you built
something and it was so impactful that
it actually led to a ton of career
growth." Um, I'm kind of curious, maybe
we can is there some way for us to
reverse engineer that for others? Like,
how how do you go about starting
projects where the motivation comes
completely from you within a large
company?
>> It's a really good question. Um, if I
had to to boil it down to one sentence,
you can just do things. And I think the
the way people talk about it now is you
have agency. And it it often seemed like
you don't like it's really hard to find
time. And I I am not recommending people
spend nights on the weekends working on
all the projects, but early in my
career, I my my main goal was to get
better at like software engineering. And
the way of doing that was to learn
everything like build anything you can
build games, websites, like just build a
ton of different things and you just
gain experience from learning how to
build those types of software, right? Um
so I think that was ingrained in me from
really really early on. And then the
other thing I did early on in my career
was I found someone that I wanted to I
found someone on the team that I I
wanted their career. So on my team there
was an architect um David Evo and his
job seemed really cool. He got to think
about the future. He kind of spanned
multiple areas of of the product. He got
to build the next wave of what was
coming next. Um, so I basically attached
myself to him and I limit his behaviors
and I said to myself, okay, I I want
that role. Let me make sure I I'm seeing
what he does that seems to work and I
want to keep doing that. And I would I
would be the coder of his ideas, right,
for a while. And that turned into
learning how to do it on my own. So I
kind of I did this gradual thing where I
was like attached myself to people who
were like that. And then I found myself
in that same position. here's a new
thing. I have some insights. Let me try
spiking a thing that will work and then
I I communicate ideas with code. So I
would always build a prototype first and
then show someone show an advocate on
the team, show the architect, show the
PM and say like is this useful? Is it
cool? I saw this issue that um a
customer was having. I think this solves
a problem. Do you think we can turn into
something? And that I think that pattern
of doing that helped me gain insights
into what people um what what helps
people get over the hump of like should
we build something or not. I I would
build a thousand things and maybe one
would hit.
>> It's it's interesting that you say
agency. I I think a lot of people
who work at big companies or talk about
big companies, they feel like it's
difficult to have agency. they have all
these projects that are assigned to them
depending on the team culture and it
sounds like you had that agency through
energy. So you were moonlighting you
were doing going above and beyond. You
did your normal stuff but then on top of
that you had all this extra agency. uh
in in my understanding that's how you
unlocked agency at a big company
>> and I think it afforded me I think once
you build a reputation for being able to
kind of perform build and build things I
think more things come your way I don't
want to say like it is easy or it will
happen but I think in my case 100% like
when I when I the more things I built
the more things I showed people on the
team people would just say things like
Hey David, we're building this new
thing. Like we want to get your take. We
want to get your opinion. Should we work
on it? Can you help us build this thing?
Um, a lot of opportunity comes your way
when when I think you have a good rep
for building stuff. I think further in
my career that showed very true for what
happened that what happened after
Signaler pretty much
>> you get a lot more of those permissioned
opportunities when you have credibility
and permissionless agency is uh it's
almost this hack to kind of bypass
credibility.
>> Yeah. And and a funny story I think the
funny thing is like
you you get a chance to be more
permissionless the better your track
record is. So the more you have, the
more success you have, the more lia you
get to fail, which gives you space to
try more things.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. No, that makes sense. I I've seen
that a lot. The the very high fast
growing software engineers, they're
almost this weapon that management and
people around them say, "We trust you.
Go do that thing that you do." And they
can go and try all these risky projects.
I bet if you were someone who was uh
struggling to meet expectations,
a lot more directed opportunities are
being handed to you and you're being
monitored. So I can totally
>> Yeah,
>> totally see that.
>> So true.
>> Going to your latestage promos, you got
the promotion to principal, you got the
promotion to distinguished at Microsoft.
I'm curious, what is the thing that led
to the promotion to principal?
>> Principal was interesting. So, I I had I
had one boss, I won't say his name. I
had a one boss who who told me when I
got to senior that my promos would slow
down. And I remember that meeting where
I sat down and I got this I got I got
the promotion. I was really happy. He
kind of gave me this downer like don't
expect more promotions like from here
because you know I was like what does
that mean? Um and I never really took it
took it to heart but the the jump to
principle is a big jump. I had been
working on Signal R at the time. I built
this um if you ever use Heroku. Heroku
like pioneered get pushing and deploying
your app like instantly right we had
built there was a there was a tech
called app harbor for fornet this this
company was doing the same thing for net
and we built a similar thing for Azure
this is like super early in Azure time
frame right like we had built this like
brand new it's actually still there it's
called kudu um and I had I had been
working with the same architect and I
had built it with him um And then at
some point in that time frame, I got
pulled off of that. And I think this is
one of the places where like your track
record helps just get set up for the
future opportunities. So I had my
director tell me, "Hey, we have this new
thing spinning up and we need you to go
work on it." And obviously, you know,
you're working on something else. You're
like, "Man, I want to finish what I'm
working on, but then this thing happens.
I'll I'll help people with this thing.
And that ended up being the beginning of
the new .NET um .NET core that we write
that was crossplatform and modern and
new. And it was a big opportunity like
so big it was scary at first like oh my
gosh like what do you mean you're the
architect like and I was senior I was I
was it was me it was me and another
principal engineer that got chosen to be
the architects of this project and I
hadn't had an an experience working at
that scale before because I think you
had like 30 engineers that were working
on this this project. Um, but we had
free reign to kind of build what
whatever we thought was right and that
was like both amazing and terrifying.
Um, and I think through that project I
learned a ton of things like knowing how
to I I don't want to say we weren't
managers but learning how to manage a
project and architecture and scale and
like initially I was trying to code
review every single change. You can
imagine that burnt me out within within
a year I was like okay I can't I can't
we can't do this anymore. We have to
figure out how to trust people and scale
and figure out what's important, what's
not what's not urgent versus urgent,
etc. Um that year I got promoted
actually had my first first kid and I
got promoted that to principal that same
year I did this um the first year of
.NET Core um design and and building it.
>> You you mentioned that that the team
grew so much that you had to scale
yourself out of necessity. What are the
things that you did that allowed you to
be like architect for so many engineers
without burning yourself out?
>> So I learned I learned some of this
during Sigmar. The the the smaller
version with Sigma only had like seven
or eight people overall, right?
Engineers, textures, product managers.
And we had two new hires. And I had
never had the experience of delegating
in a way where I thought it was like if
I gave you this work, it's to grow you,
right? I never thought that way before.
I was always like, I'm a senior
engineer. I can get this done. I I can
do it faster than you. Like why would I
give you this thing when I can do it
faster? Um, we had really smart
engineers that we hired from college and
it took me a while to kind of get past
it's going to take them longer at first,
but once they understand all the stuff,
then we we can amplify the impact. And I
think once I saw that, it flipped my
brain. So I had I had something from
from the Sigma frame that was like okay
if you can invest in people and kind of
get them on the same page as you if you
are on the same wavelength if you can
delegate more um then you can kind of
get get more done as a team right you
you be you begin to be you begin to
think about outcomes and less about like
the work you're doing individually I
think the leap from senior to principal
feels like being able to to do more
through others than yourself and it's
it's where I think a lot of people end
up plateauing because software engineers
are very like you know we want to we
want to we like coding we want to be
alone we want to build the things
ourselves software engineering is a
collaborative event it's like we want to
figure out how to get the customer
feedback figure out what to build figure
out how to build it the best way and I
think that change in in my brain
prepared me for like core because it was
such such bigger scale like how do you
even begin to manage that many people
that that many facets we we rebuilt
everything from scratch like we
literally rebuilt the package manager
the runtime the libraries like
everything from the get-go and it was
overwhelming at first um what I think
helped a lot was not treating everything
as equally urgent like that was a big
deal like if this change over here went
in and it wasn't perfect. I wouldn't be
like we can't merge this. It needs to
have this interface, these tests. Um,
learning how to set foundations for
others and to trust others and like
letting people fail was a really hard
thing for me at first. Okay, I could I
could avoid the failure
and and it turns out that the team like
I think a lot of the things that get you
to senior and maybe principal hurt you
grow even further, right? Being a
control freak, being someone who like is
amazing at their job, getting stuff done
in a very specific way doesn't really
help you when you want to scale it to a
thousand engineers. You have to kind of
figure out how to inspire others to do
the same as you through different means
like one-on ones or or you being an
example or like more more different
techniques, but it's difficult to just
be to type. You aren't going to type
harder and make a bigger impact. So,
it's like I shifted my brand to be
outcome focused was a big big change.
>> You mentioned the architect title or I
guess role. What does that mean at
Microsoft?
That's a fun one. Um, when I joined, I
saw someone who was a principal software
architect. Let me say for myself, that's
the role that I want. I don't know what
it is. That's what I want, bro. It's
kind of a semiofficial role at Microsoft
and at certain levels, the middle
principal bands, you can be one of these
architects. And to me, it really means
you're more breath rather than depth.
You're more overseeing the design of the
overall system. We have different
engineering archetypes. I would say even
at the highest level you have someone
who's a super coder who is like I am
just going to build so much stuff I can
impact so many things. There are people
who work on really deep technical
details that have a huge impact. We have
um one of the foremost GC experts like
in the entire world right working on um
the net garbage collector. So you can
have that kind of impact. Um you could
be someone overseeing a hugely impactful
area of the product. So there's a lot of
space to kind of like figure out what
archetype you want to be. And I think
the architect role for me felt like
breath. So I am architect for aspet core
back in those days and I am like
overseeing the design of the whole stack
the web framework web server
how we how we ship package like the
entire engineering um idea and I'm not
the the engineering lead I'm the
architect so I'm trying to vet the
decisions that are going to like last
for like 20 years if we do this change
now we can't do this thing in like five
or 10 years and I hadn't had experience
doing that before but I had a really
good mentors who had done that. that
I've been watching and shadowing and
trying to understand through experience
like how do you build systems that last
20 years like holy crap right
>> so as you've grown to distinguished
engineer at Microsoft how has the
percent of your time that you spend
writing code changed
>> it's funny I think I think there's what
your job is like do I have to code every
day to do my job I I don't know if I get
rewards anymore for coding. I get
rewards for outcomes. But for myself,
selfishly, I code every day. So my team
knows right now that I I send lots of
poll requests every day to the code
base. I'm I'm currently working on um I
have a new project I'm working on. This
shirt um Aspire and I code a lot. So I I
personally make sure that when I'm
working on a project, I am somewhat
involved coding still. I don't want to
be the architect who doesn't know the
code and is giving people instructions
like you should do this and I'm going to
go away now and disappear somewhere else
and and you won't see me again. I want
to be the person who is like you I'm a
pair on the team. I want to be your
everyone's peers and I want to be facing
the builds and doing facing the test and
not there isn't any work that's bene
kind of what what I'm thinking. Um, so I
when I when I'm on team, I typically
work as um as an engineer on the team.
>> If you stopped coding right now and you
just kept leading the team, would your
performance review look fine?
>> Yeah, I think so. But distinguish
engineer is definitely about companywide
or organizationalwide impact or
companywide impact. Like so I think even
though my my day job is definitely
making sure the architecture of of as a
whole is is sound and good and moving
forward and we're doing the right things
and pushing is a part of my job that is
like looking forward and you know
talking publicly and like um inspiring
people internally and mentoring people
and so there's a lot of things I do that
aren't like what I used to do way before
that I think help with with impact. Um,
as an example, I gave
four talks internally about how to use
AI to do software engineering and that
happened just because I had been using
it myself for a lot of different things
and someone said, "Hey, you should give
a talk to the team." You think about the
impact of those things. They they help
when you see engineers who aren't just
your boss telling you to go do something
seemingly for bad reasons. um engineers
who are credible telling you how they do
their jobs. So I do a lot of that stuff
too. A lot of things are not
software engineering to be to be frank.
>> When you got the promotion to
distinguished engineer, what's the story
behind that?
>> Absolutely insane. Um first of all,
distinguished engineer is the final
level of like partner. If you go on to
the levels, FYI, you'll see level 59 to
80. I think the last is 80, the final
level. Um, distinguished engineer, I
think it's 70 on there,
>> right?
>> And there's a there's an actually
there's actually an official process
to become to to get that title. You
don't just it's not a promotion that you
just get and because you did a great job
that year. It is a set of technical
leaders have to peer review and decide
that decide if you are I'll say worthy
or not if you're worthy or not of that
title. Um it was probably the craziest
promotion I've ever experienced mostly
because of the the people that are there
at Microsoft. Just as an example um
Guido Guido Van Rosson who created
Python is the same level as me.
>> Wow. So like imposter syndrome, right?
>> Imposter and Guido's great. Like he's
he's great. He's really fun, cool guy.
Maximum imposter syndrome. I'm I'm
young. I think I'm young for for that
role, too. So like when I was going for
that role. I felt as though that would
affect me as well. It It didn't, but I
felt it would it would affect me. So I I
had all these hold up hold ups about
like am I really at this level? Can I
can I perform there? Can I do well
there? And then w with all of my I think
this is probably where all the work I've
done in the past helped because you do
need a body of work and you do need um a
good track record to qualify for these
kinds of roles. You can't just become a
DE because you had a one fun one fun
year. Um I think some of the criteria
ends up being like what have you
contributed like that that impacts
companywide like things. what have you
contributed that has so it is a lot of
it is like deferred impact I guess if it
makes sense because um net member when I
when I went to from principal to partner
in the email it had net course impact
and that was a by then it had been about
seven years it wasn't like I did it last
year or the year before it was like this
is built up impact and then like I had
been the architect to help people adopt
the new net internally and I had done
that for a bunch of different teams. So
like there's there was all this kind of
build up to to like I guess deferred
impact a really good way of saying it.
Um and I think all those things helped
Nougat signal like how did it how did
the thing that you helped build and mold
and raise like grow how did it impact
the industry the company and those all
come into account when when um the the I
think the the their fellows who decide
who becomes a DE.
>> Were you involved in that process at all
or was it a surprise when you got the
distinguished promo? I was involved from
a point of from the point of view of
helping my leadership with like content.
So I I gave them all of my contributions
to things things I've written like
papers I've written code contributions
to various various projects. I kind of
gave them the raw material. I didn't do
anything else.
Um but what what made it impactful for
me was seeing the other fellows like
acknowledge and say like welld deserved
and it's about time and like okay
>> maybe I should maybe I should maybe I
shouldn't be here. This is this is good.
>> You mentioned the lofty expectations of
this distinguished engineer level. Yeah.
Is that something that you worry about
now that you've been acting in the role
for a while?
>> At first I I I would tell people I am a
baby D. I've only been here like a
couple months or or it's been one year
now and I not sure yet. Um I think now
it's been two two and a half two and a
half three years now. Um I feel pretty
confident I can perform at this level
and I think I understand what is what is
required. Um I would say initially very
much ex my my first review cycle um I
felt pressure to like document
everything and just write down what I
thought was all the impact right it
wasn't it felt very much like oh my gosh
I should I need to make sure I'm write
all stuff down um telling my boss what
I'm doing like making sure he knows and
because I think you're you're you're
almost an executive at the company like
you're you're you're at the level below
being executive and like it's super
scary to think about h having to have
that impact every year repeatedly over
and over. So I think I found a pattern
for kind of like making sure I had the
right level of impact. Um talking to my
bosses, making sure I had I was visible,
making sure I'm doing all the right
things. So yeah, I don't I don't feel
the pressure as much now. Um but who
knows? I mean, things could change.
Things could change. So, so you went
through it looks like 11 promotions
which is kind of ridiculous. You went
all the way from the beginning all the
way to then and the crazy thing you're
saying Guido the founder or the creator
of Python is that level as well.
>> I can't even fathom cuz apparently
there's one last one the technical
fellow.
>> What what does that final boss level
even look like?
So the people who are fellows, tech
fellows, I guess the the the one that
you know in my division that everyone
idolizes, Andrew Halsburg made Turbo
Pascal, Deli,
C and TypeScript.
>> So like no one's competing with that
dude because like no one you can't
repeat building for successful
languages. Um, but I think if you were
thinking about the the archetype of like
someone who is a fellow, it's that level
of impact, right? Or the people who
built the Windows kernel. Actually,
there there's one guy Dave Cutler who
came from Deck back in like the 80s or
whatever and he helped build he built
Windows NT, he built Azure, the the OS,
he built the hypervisor for Xbox. He is
the only senior technical fellow.
>> Wow.
>> That isn't even a real title. That's
just his title.
>> Wow.
>> So, it's kind of like it I think at
those levels, everyone's a unicorn and
everyone has their own path. So, you
aren't trying to follow people's path
onetoone. You're looking for proxies for
for impact. To be a fellow, you need
industrywide impact, not just impact in
your division, in your company. It's
like you need to do something that
impacts the industry. I think we hired
someone recently who is a fellow who
like invented RSS. It's like that. It's
like that level of like thing, right?
It's like you built something that
became the industry standard for, you
know, the internet. like um there was a
guy on my team who was the intern for
Tim Berners Lee and he is on the HTP
spec like is that is that
yeah so yeah this those are the kind of
people that end up being fellows I think
>> were there any unexpected perks of
getting voted to distinguish engineer
>> besides more money um
>> let me think
>> well for instance I guess the thing that
I'm curious about is uh at a lot of
companies when you get promoted to a
certain level, you get added to special
forums that only distinguished engineers
have.
>> Okay, the coolest part. Here's the cool
the coolest part.
>> There's a there's an email alias called
engineer.
That is all the dees on Microsoft.
>> Oh wow.
>> It is just the coolest alias the
engineer on Microsoft. Like all this is
really
>> that's awesome.
>> That's one of the perks. Yeah, but there
there is there is there's a there's an
internal um there's a forum where we all
meet I think every every couple of
months. The way this typically works is
you have a sponsor, right? So when I'm
when I'm when I was going to be I told
my mentor I want to be a de I had I had
mentors who were fellows. Okay. So one
one tip when I became a partner I told
my men I I told my management that I
want a mentor. I want help find a mentor
who is a fellow because I want to be
one. So I figured if I want to be one, I
should have people who are men mentors
that can help me get there. Um and my
one of my mentors was very impactful in
my career. Um he invented PowerShell,
Jeffrey Snowver, and he was one of the
best mentors that I've had. He actually
left Microsoft and went to Google
recently. Um but he was like really
really impactful for me in my career. He
was my one of my main sponsors and I
ended up um getting to go to one of
these tech leaders forums and I got to
mangle and talk to all the people who
were like there and it was really really
interesting, really cool.
>> You mentioned that that mentor was
incredibly impactful. What was the
things that he was telling you that made
a difference?
A lot of people I want to say sugarcoat
like how to get places, how how to get
promoted and they'll give you very
generic feedback. Um you have to do a
project that's super impactful. He was
very very much direct like we should go
talk to the people who decide and ask
them like where you are and then and it
was jarring to me because I I never
thought about asking the teacher for why
why it it like no one ever tells you um
you have to do X to get promoted.
Exactly. And it never exactly works one
to one. It's like you have to have more
impact so make sure you're working on
something that's like you know super
impactful and maybe you aren't now and
change. He was like, "Let's go to the
source. Go to the host. Let's go talk to
the CTOS. Let's go figure out like what
it means for you in your in your role."
And I was like, "That is super helpful."
And because it helped me, it helped me
understand what I should and shouldn't
be doing in a very like real way. It
wasn't just arbitrary advice that just
happens to you. It was like very
explicit. I had a second mentor. I had
done some there's this thing where you
can get feedback from different people
in in the company your manager um your
peer etc. and it gets turned into a
package and they give you feedback and
it tells you your strengths and what
you're what what you're good at, what
you're really bad at, what you're what
what how you act under stress, all these
things. And my my first reaction is, "Oh
my gosh, I'm going to have to fix all
the things I'm bad at. I got to figure
out how to, you know, get leveled." And
my mentor was like, "No, no, take your
strengths and amplify them even more.
you could work on the things you're not
good at and be average at those or you
can work on things that you're really
good at and be super human at those
things. And it it broke my brain because
up until and that was like I want to say
five years ago up until then I had been
thinking about man how do I make sure I
am better at everything so I can like be
a well-rounded individual. It was like
no one no one gets promoted to these
roles for being average. you need to you
have to be super human in something that
you're that like you're really good at
that people aren't right. So that helped
me refocus to to thinking about
finding ways to make up for things that
I'm not good at. So as an example, if I
form a team, I am not the one that's
going to schedule meetings or I am not
going to go through every detail of how
how we ship and all the all the
checklist. I am super bad at that stuff
and I will make sure I have someone who
is really really good at that stuff so I
can focus on what I'm good at. Right. So
that helped me reframe how to think
about um amplifying what I do well to
kind of um get more impact.
>> Makes sense. I mean it's kind of like a
power law type of thing. At the top is
where there's the most insane returns.
Just take those things and go further on
that exponential.
>> Exactly. It's exactly that. U you
mentioned a lot of these you know
impressive engineers and I think as a
distinguished engineer you have a unique
perspective because you can see what is
impressive with a critical eye of a
great engineer. What are some examples
of other engineers that you look up to
and what makes them impressive to you?
>> I can I can talk about some of the
well-known ones and then talk about like
just people that I work with in general
that are impressive for different
reasons. my current team there are like
five other partner level engineers that
have been here 20 plus years that are
just really really good for different
reasons like experts in the GC one
person is like a super coder like just
he just codes 10x people complain about
engineers aren't 10x he's 10x
he just produces way more code than
everyone else combined Right. Um,
there's one guy who like literally
seemed to know everything about obscure
things you would never understand in
your life without having to have seen it
yourself. All kind of stuff. Stuff about
C, stuff about compiler, stuff about the
OS, and you're like, how does he seem to
know everything about everything, right?
Um, and then there there engineers who
just seem to know what to build and have
a good eye judgment. So, I I'm I'm on
the C um review design review team.
We meet every couple of months and we
review C# features, right? New features
coming into language and I'm on there
with Andrew Hellsburg who made C#,
right? So like what I say doesn't
matter. What he says matters. I mean it
it does it counts. Um but the way he
communicates
like the way he gives feedback for what
feels good and what does not feel good.
He always does it in a way that is very
much like he is not talking down to you.
I mean, this dude invented four
languages are just like what what
everyone uses and yet he can still talk
about it in a way where it's like, you
know, some people are really smart and
they talk down to you and you feel dumb
because he's like, "Oh, he's super smart
and I'm dumb." He does it in a very
pragmatic, practical way, but then you
see the code he commits and you're like,
"This dude is inventing titism theory
that we haven't even seen before. Tech
is like insane." Um, so I admire a lot
of like watching people like that spread
their impact. Um, Mark Rosanovich, who's
CTO of Azure, famous for his Windows
tools. Um, he still codes and it blows
me away sometimes like he's he actually
is working on something right now. Um,
and he sent an email two days ago and I
was like, "Holy crap." and and and and
it was it was very dev a dev centric
email. It wasn't a high level we should
do X. It's like no, I wrote some code. I
improved the performance. I'm like
here's the result. Now I was this late.
How does she have time to do stuff?
So I think whenever I see highle
engineers or IC's still coding like
that, I get really inspired. It's really
easy to fall into the meeting trap. Um
actually when I went partner
I fell super steeply into the meeting
trap of like I was in meetings all day
every day and I got really sad and my
mentor said as an IC your job is to have
like you you need to think and to build
stuff. So minimally on your calendar
block eight hours a week minimum to to
do that stuff. And it took me a while to
change my brain to say I can just say no
to meetings.
Decline, decline, decline, decline,
decline.
>> I can knock our code.
>> So I I think the next set of questions I
want to ask you um because you have a
public presence on Twitter. There's all
these top tweets that you have that I
think are really interesting short
thoughts that I'd be curious to have you
expand on. Yeah.
>> So I think the first one is um talking
about university courses and you said
that you know there should be a
university course that explains how to
refactor code, how to make changes to it
without breaking an existing code base.
My question to you is if you were to
design that course, what would some of
the key concepts be?
Having been working for this long now in
industry, computer science is not
software engineering. It's not even this
not even close, right? Computer science
is like learning how to learning the
science of of computers and bits and
bites and the math and algorithms and
you do a little bit of the things that
are software engineering like but it's
nothing like software engineering. So
when you get your first job, you spend a
lot of time just trying to understand
what's there so you can surgically make
your first change and not destroy
everything, right? Like don't break the
bill, don't break everything else. So I
think if I were to have a course, you
would be thrown into an artificially big
code base. We would we would have a
maybe it would have to change every year
because students will just copy from the
previous year. So it has to change every
year, different code base. And your job
is to make a bug fix. you got to fix a
bug in this codebase and write a test
for it. And just the
the the skills you learn being a code
architect, a code archaeologist
is so different from just just writing
buying an elite code question or doing a
homework assignment that is just like
this one thing in a textbook. You learn
a lot of adjacent skills from just
trying to figure out where to put the
code in the first place.
I I think it's funny. I think thinking
now I think it would be super useful
like every every assignment is making
one one fix and maybe you can set up the
code base such that it's not super hard
to figure out what it is anyone with
enough time like you know we could
figure out and make this one triple
change and and add one test. Um but I
think a lot of a lot of people's jobs
are tweaking software that that is there
already. Not everyone gets to create new
software. Like if you if you work on
Windows, sure you'll build new
components, but you aren't going to
change the kernel unless you're going to
do a new a new a new OS. Um, so yeah,
super useful skill.
>> Yeah, I think there was another set of
tweets that I saw that was kind of
around this idea of that tech interviews
are focused so much on writing new code,
but actually the real high leverage
skill is debugging it. Yeah. What gives
you that that thought? Maybe you can
expand on that. So early in my career um
I worked with a ton of engineers who
were and on the on the donet team we had
a lot of engineers who just work at the
platform level. Um so I got to see
firsthand people diagnose crazy crashes
risk conditions threading issues. I got
firsthand a firsthand seek to even
watching people's mindset when they go
to diagnose issues. I thought to myself
like there's kind of two skill sets that
are m maybe you learn some coding but
they're just not the same skill set. And
if you think about building an
application, deploying it, shipping it,
and then getting craft reports, trying
to resolve issues, like trying to figure
out what's going on in production,
there's this second skill set that is
just not writing like not authoring
code. that is how do you even think
through debugging issues? How do you
know which thread caused the exception?
What tools do you use? How do you think
about how it got there? Is like I
thought to myself, it would be fun to
have an interview where you give someone
a crash dump or something like, "Hey,
this this this app just crashed. Like,
figure out what the problem is." And you
aren't trying to see if they can solve
it. You want to see what they even start
doing. like do you start adding logs? Do
you rerun the program? How do you think
about risk conditions? Do you like print
thread ids and try to figure out
interle? Like all these all these
interesting things come out of watching
someone try to diagnose problems. I it's
funny I have the highest respect for
engineers who can be thrown into like a
a problem situation where they don't
know the codebase super well um and they
can kind of solve the issue. Super fun
story. I remember being this is early
days in Azure. There was this very I
can't remember what the site was, but
there was a very popular site that was
going down. I was running on Azure and
I'm like all I was up late. It was 1:00
a.m. and my CVP
sends me a message like a a DM. It's
like, "Hey, you free?" I'm just like,
"What?
Yeah, I'm free." I get added to a call
that has like a hundred engineers trying
to debug why the site is crashing and
you know like we we call the the the
team who was working on it was some
other company but we were helping them
as as engineers from Microsoft trying to
debug the issue and you could just see
the different people's skill sets trying
to figure out what the issue was and we
solved it eventually. um it was a
concurrency issue somewhere in some
dictionary that caused a risk condition
and I thought to myself like this is one
of the skills that you need to have as
an engineer like writing code is just
it's a small piece of your overall skill
set learning how to debug and think
through issues is like another big big
chunk
>> yeah and as evidence of that being very
impactful I know some companies you know
every company has their different
archetypes and you mentioned like super
coder also known as code machine in some
places.
>> Code. Yep.
>> There's also I've heard the archetype
fixer, too. And that's that's a that's a
really cool one because it's been
described as someone drops in somewhere,
they make a oneline change after tons of
investigation and it gets two times
better, three times better or something
like that.
>> Oh my gosh, we have some engineer on on
the team who there'll be a thread to get
started off. whole perk issue somewhere
in gRPC call and I'll add the engineer
that's right and say hey can you look at
this boom boom boom here's a trace and
I'm just like
>> oh my gosh it's solved it's solved
>> so impressive
>> um another tweet that you had I thought
was really interesting is it says
lukewarm take the lower on the
technology stack you sit the less
mistakes you're allowed to make what
what made you think of that did
something break super low level in the
stack somewhere
>> I have to be working on some so I work
on platform so the way we think about
software is way different from you know
higher level services or even web web
front ends or whatever I think maybe I
have been working on something that
broke I mean a lot of things break that
are just kind of insane the things that
we change that break services
are absolutely unheard of um we will
change the order of how things come back
in a method and like it just snaps some
some company's website goes down. Um so
I think
when you work at that layer that you
gain an appreciation for the kinds of
changes you can and can't make.
Um I think I think that tweet maybe was
inspired by one of these bugs cuz I I
work on I think at that time I had been
working on um first party
adoption of of ofNET and we had seen a
couple of people upgrade and hit issues
that made us just completely shocked. It
was like how did how did you find that
bug? Like no one hits that. What do you
mean you have 400 400 arguments to
method? Like that's not
there's some limits somewhere where that
like that can't be a real problem,
right?
>> There's another tweet here and that is
really interesting. It's about
promotions. You said that when you got
promoted to a senior software engineer
at Microsoft. You remember thinking that
other people were smarter than you and
should have been promoted first and you
would have thought they would be angry
but the opposite happened that actually
having good co-workers matters a lot and
people weren't
>> you know so yeah what's your your
thought there
>> this is you you are you are bringing
back some good memories so I remember
when I was going to senior I actually I
was actually a little worried about
getting before other people because I I
have it on a really fast path
And I thought I mean maybe maybe it
would make people jealous. It was like
why not me and and and when I joined my
team I think there were four people from
MIT and two from CMU and I had gone to
Florida Tech and I was like okay these
people are like way smarter than me. So
like my way of working through imposter
syndrome was just to like work really
hard and like be a busy be doing stuff.
Um, I think I understood that when I got
promoted to senior that the impact was
not about being intelligent. It was not
just about like getting the highest
grade or being smart. It was like are
the things that you're working on being
a top of the business. And that was the
shift where I under where I began to
understand like okay it's not just about
what I know. It's not just about that
this person on the team is really smart
in area X. It's like can I take all that
and produce something that is impactful
and that promotion helped me see okay
that was the new get thing the signal
thing that's how you get promoted that's
how you you you know you you add impact
for the team it's not just about knowing
this thing about this this feature about
this area about this OS because I always
felt like man I don't know enough about
you know technology X or about area X I
got to go deeper and learn more and the
question was always is that for you or
is that for your career? Like what's it
for? Um, you don't have to know how I
don't know, maybe you should, but you
don't have to know how TCPIP works to
get promoted to to senior. Um, I'm sure
people don't know the details of how how
it works, right? Um, I think that that
promotion for me helped me separate like
being smart from making an impact. It's
like okay promotions impact those
promotions. Being smart is something
else. It's just like knowing knowing
more stuff and being helpful for solving
problems. Um and the second part was my
co-workers were happy for me at least
outwardly.
It was but I was I was really worried at
the time because it was like new person
joins team gets promoted really fast.
Do people see that as
why not me or do they see it as yeah
that makes sense? Right? When I asked
questions about
other people who kind of went up really
fast to my period at the time, they
would say things like everyone knew it
was going to happen. Like there's
certain people where people kind of know
where it happens and you never know if
that's the case for you or not or or if
people are just like, man, I don't think
that person deserves it. So, you've been
working at Microsoft for over 17 years
now, and one of this tweets that you
have is talking about big company tips
that you have. And it says, "Before you
change roles, ask when the last reorg
was.
>> What's the thinking behind that advice?"
>> Big companies are are a machine. And I
remember someone telling me really early
on that league and maybe it was it was
tongue and cheek. It was like when
you're when you're when you are uh an
executive vice president at at these
companies or a CVP or whatever you are,
you show that you're doing something
like it's like motion like reorgs are
motion and motion means that you're
you're changing stuff and the only thing
constant is change in these big
companies like there's always a reorg
plan. There's always there's always a
reorg coming there's always a reorg that
just happened and you're trying to
figure out in between the reorg moments
what were like who were the leaders what
was the the impetus what caused it to
happen I mean you can never know when
next one's coming but learning about the
previous one is super I think it's super
important just to understand like where
we are where where you would be heading
right in in that dimension might or had
a big reorg like recently previous meta
person now runs um Jay, you know, runs
um my my my or
I think it's super important to know
that because it helps you figure out
what the purpose is now, right? If if it
just happened, it tells you a lot about
where the org is heading, where the team
is heading, where things are going. Um,
I think it's easy to kind of change
teams or move around and not think about
the overall
place that org is going, but then
Microsoft is big enough that is like
every new org is a whole new company.
So, it's definitely worthwhile trying to
figure out where what the goals are of
that or where it stands now, what
happened last time kind of thing. I bet
I I I tweeted that after either talking
to a mentee
um who had been reorked and I think they
had been like four in a row or something
like that crazy um or or it happened to
me. But yeah,
>> I see. So you're saying you should read
the behind the scenes of the reorg and
what that means for your career in the
future.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Oh yeah. I heard someone say something
to me recently that was really good
advice. was when you're looking to
change jobs, don't think about the
things you love because they'll be easy
to do. Think about the things you hate.
Like what what can you not stand about
like working in the area or an
environment or whatever it is and go
look for that. If you see that, that'll
be that that'll be the thing that will
be hard to to get around or work
through. Let's say you hated open space
and you wanted a closed office. if the
company was open like don't go to the
company that is open skit because like
then you'll you'll be unhappy right um
there there are better examples that are
probably more toxic about like people
but that's a simpler um way of
describing it
>> you've been at Microsoft for a long time
your entire career even including your
internships I'm I'm curious what has
kept you at Microsoft as long as you've
been
>> yeah every every time yeah I I think
about this myself a lot like what keeps
me here and I think I am part of a
generation of millennials who broke the
curse of like our boomer parents like
trying to stay in the same place
forever. I have a lot of friends that
jump jumped their own and they got paid
for it and it was really good for them
in their careers. I want to say I maybe
didn't take the same path and it it kind
of worked out. Um I had a couple of
times where probably the most impactful
time where I maybe almost left was when
I was senior my boss left and went to
Twitter preip at Twitter and a year in
she tell she pings me and tells me to
come like go interview at Twitter and I
actually interviewed at Twitter and at
GitHub. It's funny and Twitter um at the
same time and I got to I got both offers
and the offers were pretty good and it
was the probably the first time in my
career where I was like at a crossroads
because my career had been going fine. I
was working on signal. I was like on the
up and up but then here's this offer
that like seemed a lot better and
they're pre preipo companies like should
I should I go? Um, and there there was a
lot of deliberation as to like if I
should go or I should stay or not or
whatever. Um, I ended up staying and
it worked out. But I will say the
morning like Twitter went public.
>> Mhm.
>> Instant depression.
>> I was depressed for like a week.
>> Oh my god. Oh my god.
>> What What kept you at Mark? cuz it
sounds like those offers were better
than what you were making at the time.
>> Yes, they were. They were. So, when I I
I got they they countered and the
counter was fine. It wasn't like inc. I
mean, I guess looking back now, it was
pretty good, but it was it was fine. Um,
but they they had me talk to like our
executive vice president and he was
like, "You're going to be like a
distinct engineer in like five years." I
mean, he definitely oversold
But I was I think maybe for me it wasn't
just the money that that made me stay.
It was like I had been working on
something I had built that was impactful
that was like built permissionless. Um
I had I think at the time I had been
getting a lot of autonomy at Microsoft
and leaving would have been like
starting over. Um, probably one of the
one of the things that people don't talk
about when changing roles or leaving or
getting a better offer somewhere else is
you build up a network, a network of
people, a network of of, you know, a
track record. I can kind of work on what
I want to work on at the at the moment.
At that time, maybe not so much, but I
think I had been given more more
autonomy. And when you're weighing the
the like should I should I stay or
should I go is like money is one thing
um the other is like are the people that
are people good
>> not just good engineers but like good
people that that that you want to work
with so there's the the people aspect
the money aspect the network aspect all
these things kind of matter in in the
soup and I think I stayed because at
Microsoft I had been getting my fix of
working on a new thing every couple of
years. Every if on my LinkedIn there's
like a new project every two years and
that was like by design. Um I think it
helped me not get bored or not like kind
of like be
um I didn't I didn't feel the need to to
go somewhere else to to do I want to do
because I felt like I could do it at
Microsoft. So that that kept me here for
this long. Um, I mean, I I won't say
that I hadn't thought about leaving
every now and then. It does it does come
into my brain every now and then, but I
think so far the people um the pay for
me is is fine. Um the the people that
pay the project, the impact I get to
have working on what I work on is a is a
big big thing for me as well. Do you
think that if you had a mentee today
facing the same decision, so they're
they're at Microsoft and they they're
doing well and then they have a you know
preIPO
open AI offer or something better than
what they have now. Well, would you tell
them you should stay at Microsoft or
would you say you know maybe go with the
risky thing?
>> I would tell them to go.
So, fun story, I actually had a mentee
who got an offer from a separate a
different company, but they weren't in a
place where they could do their best
work.
So, the combination of the offer plus
that I was like, "You have to go." I
said, "They're going to counter,
but you have to go. You can't stay here.
You You should go. You should go." If I
had that for myself, maybe I would have
I would have been gone. I would have
been gone for that.
U you had this interesting tweet on um
job hopping that I thought was maybe
relevant now which is that you said once
in your career you should work on a
project long enough to see the long-term
impact of your decisions. It's a
humbling experience.
>> That's a good one.
>> So I it could be better for long-term
growth uh in some cases.
>> Yeah. So what I would say so that one
that tweet was inspired by my career has
always been this like work on a thing
and move on. I would still have ties to
the thing I worked on help people that
are working on it now whenever things go
wrong or whatever. But the the thing
that I'm I have worked on for 10 years
net core was the longest I've ever
worked on anything in my career ever.
Ever. And I think it was a good it was a
good change because it really helped me
appreciate like deciding to do something
in the first two years and then holy
crap seeing the impact of that decision
whether it be bad or good, right? Um it
it gives you a whole new skill set um
perspective on how to make decisions.
And for for some things it's it's
obvious and you can say okay well we
didn't understand at the time the scope
or the scenario or whatever else but
things that didn't seem important became
important. Um one of the jokes that I
make about you know when you work on
something for 10 years all the small
issues you thought were small that were
just like we can do it later will become
big issues at some point. Like somebody
will hit everything that you punted and
it it it happened. it it all of it
happened. Um, and I thought like I think
maybe if you think about 10 year
projects, 20 year projects, who knows if
it's good for career growth, maybe not
like maybe if you work on the same for
20 years, like oh my gosh, not not
great. But it'll teach you a different
skill set that is like you get to
understand the implications. You get to
understand, you know, if you were going
to build the next next version, you
would have much more insight into like
what you messed up. It's really hard to
appreciate what you messed up when you
like do a thing and you you leave. You
V1. All good. New project. But I
don't I don't fault anyone for like
doing both things because I've done both
too.
>> Yeah. I could see it better for I guess
developing judgment. But I and I could
also see it being you know imagine a
career that's a leg of jumps that could
and if assuming every jump is higher
than the other, that person's probably
gonna have a lot of career growth. But
if all the projects they start just kind
of go downhill once they leave, I wonder
what it does for their pattern
recognition and judgment.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. It's funny. I
I told someone I don't know exactly how
to how to describe the ingredients that
make up a successful project, but I can
tell you when I'm working on one versus
when I'm not. And that is built up over
time and experience and like seeing
which things work out, which things
don't work out. Um, it's kind of
fine-tuning, I guess, an internal model
in my head. Okay, this this has the
smell of something that that can be
successful versus not. And there are
some things here that I'm seeing that
work out well and some things that are
not working well. And yeah,
>> coming to the the end of this, I I kind
of want to ask you some um just high
level reflections and things. One one
thing I'm curious because you're so high
up at Microsoft at this point and you've
been there for so long too. I know the
common perception is preachy Microsoft
was very different from post SATA
Microsoft at least in terms of stock
performance. Um did you notice anything
internally like the culture shifting
when Satia became CEO?
>> Huge. I mean,
I I always tell new hires that it's
really hard to
think about the culture shift between
Sati and Balmer because you I lived it,
right? You like I was in it and it's
really hard to see the big jumps from
where we are now to where we used to be.
Um because it literally happened
gradually. It was like things were
rolled out and there's a lot more cons
the culture just changed completely,
right? Probably one of the biggest ones
that I I noticed because I I experienced
this when I joined there was
teams competing
on the same end end goal like two
different teams that I think I think
historically there there's been a
Microsoft used to do this thing where
two end teams could work on the same end
state and then one would win and the
other who who knows what would happen
this reor something else um there was a
big focus on collaboration
over like just like being the first the
first to do something. I never
experienced it myself on my team, but I
definitely wor with teams who you could
tell were kind of building the solution
before knowing what the problem was.
There's a lot of that um that I saw when
I was and I was I I was an observer. I
was like very early in career like
observing how people interacted and
culture- wise and just the way people
interacted changed like meeting culture
like how means would would appear like
emails things that seem so obvious in
hindsight like if I look at how people
would communicate in meetings now versus
emails versus how I used to work like
remote friendliness versus like how
people work in teams like I I remember
being in a meeting and someone raising
their hand on teams and I was like
raise your hand for talk like what this
is not Microsoft because I I had I had
grown up in a culture where you would
just talk right you just talk you don't
you wait for a pause and you talk you
don't you don't raise your hand to talk
or you don't like maybe it sounds crazy
a lot more consideration for everyone
else it wasn't just what's it called um
highest paid person's opinion
>> I think that's that's kind of how
Microsoft felt like when I joined like
if you were in a meeting with people
that are very senior um hard to get a
worded sometimes and if and if the if
the most the most senior person was loud
and like aggressive like people that
people that didn't think that way in the
moment would not get safe.
>> Wow.
>> I think one of the big changes was in
like how we communicated as a as a
company as a team. collaboration became
a thing that was part of your review. So
like if you were not using if you were
not trying to use things that other
teams built like you were dinged for it.
If you were going to copy and create a a
clone of someone else's thing because
you're special now the incentives push
you in the opposite direction. And I
think that's probably the most impactful
change that and that and the style of
comms was like a big change that I
observed just like existing in those
time those times.
>> I see. Okay. So the culture shifted
through performance incentives and maybe
just some of the stuff that was messaged
top down.
>> Yeah. Yeah. and and and
the behaviors that were that were being
modeled by like
the leaders like literally in meetings,
people raising their hands, people
calling people who haven't spoken. Like
imagine if you're in a meeting and
there's someone really quiet that has
really good thoughts, but maybe they
don't they don't like to speak up in
meetings, pulling it out that person in
in the meeting. Like I remember when
that first happened, I had never seen it
before. I had never seen someone say,
"Um, hey Ryan, you're quiet. You've been
quiet the whole time. What's your
opinion on this matter?" Like that.
There was just people talking and then
you would leave. Now there's a lot more.
It's much better, much more considerate
for others. Um, a lot less people
screamy, shouty. I was in like really
early in my career, people were like
shouting. And I remember thinking to
myself like, "There's normal.
>> Am I going to have to shout at some
point?" There's a famous XKCD comic
about the culture at different
companies. And if I recall correctly,
the Microsoft one is a drawing of people
with guns pointed at each other.
>> The guns. Yeah. It's so funny. I think
that picture is funny. And it's
definitely not guns at all. It went from
guns to
ambivalence like don't bother me to
collaboration. So I think that
progression is probably the biggest
change in between Bomber and Satia. the
the joke about the guns to I don't have
a gun at you, but you know, as long as
you aren't going to like disturb disturb
my my situation, like we're good to go.
You're over there, I'm over here. It's
all good to collaboration where like we
incentivize collaboration. You get
rewarded for collaboration, though. So,
I think that was the biggest the biggest
shift and change I saw in the culture.
>> When you look back on your your career
so far, do you have any major regrets
that people can learn from?
It's a good question.
>> Major regrets.
>> Major
maybe not. I I would say early in my
career, I would say super arrogant. I I
was I was very arrogant. Um you could
probably find my GitHub if if you if you
look at some of the GitHub comments and
the tone, I would say I was lacking some
empathy in a bunch of different places.
One of the big shifts that I think my
brain made over time learning how to
build teams and kind of impact through
others was like patience.
Patience, empathy. Um those two traits
helped help a lot with like growing
teams and growing like influence and
people, right? It's not just because
you're right. Being right means nothing.
It's just not important, right? Being
right is like one of many things. Um,
and I I used to want I used I used to
like I'm right therefore everything else
is like we'll follow along from there.
And I think learning over time that this
that doesn't really matter as much
because there's a lot of shades of gray
when you're in software engineers. This
is not the most important thing. So I
think early in my career I was very much
like yeah I'm right like I don't really
understand where we're having this. Why
are we still talking about this thing?
I'm right. Um, and every now and then
it'll creep out, but like it I think I I
have a lot more selfawareness now
whenever that's not the most important
thing for the for the moment, even
though it's like a thing still. I
learned over time how to dial it. Um,
but in general,
yeah, maybe the fact that that I didn't
leave and go to Twitter because I would
have gotten like a ton of money as a
senior engineer. Um, or go to or go to
or go to Facebook. I I had a bunch of
opportunities. I just didn't I didn't
take it super early on. Okay. One regret
that I do have that is not directly
career related, but like maybe in the
same ballpark. Um I had a friend in 2008
who sent me a message. He was going to
do a Bitcoin company.
>> I was like, I don't know about this
crypto thing. Dude has so much Bitcoin
though.
>> What a what? What?
Oh my god,
>> that's so funny.
>> Yeah, that that one.
>> Um, when you look back on your career,
what was your work life balance like
throughout?
>> I used to answer this by saying um there
was no balance. There was just like work
hard, play hard kind of thing. I would
say now someone told me recently that
work life balance isn't about 9 to5 and
stopping. It's about what things give
you energy and what things drain energy
from you. So early on in my career, I
was working all hours. I still do
because I enjoyed what I was doing and
maybe a little too much. So I would just
like have to dial back every now and
then, but I I enjoyed what I was doing.
So I work a lot like at work. I have to
work like on different things. Um
because programming for me was not just
my job. It was like my passion. So I I
never forget one one summer I came back
from vacation. I started making games
just like for fun. Um and I learned a
lot about making games. I took that into
things at work that I was doing and more
stuff. And for me it was always I just
love building stuff. So I want to build
more stuff. Um, what I would say is
draining now is like meetings that just
don't feel as though they have a
purpose. That if I were in meetings all
day and I felt drained after work and I
kept doing more work, that to me would
feel like no balance because I I want to
do stuff that isn't meetings, but I'm
I'm not doing that during the day and
then then I'm going home after hours
doing more work. That is like burnout
quality. So, I would say like balance
was always I work a lot. I'm absolutely
overcollic. For me, this I I love this
career. It's it's it's kind of insane
that I I get to code for for a living.
So, I I see that as like a privilege
that I'm going to keep doing until I
can't do it anymore.
>> Yeah. I think when I look at a lot of
people's careers who have been, you
know, as successful as you, they that's
one of the unfair advantages I see
almost everyone has is they have this
innate intrinsic motivation. So they
they work a ton of hours just non-stop
and and a lot of like like you a lot of
people love it and that is such an
unfair advantage.
>> It is. I I saw um one of Andre Karpath's
talk he said $10,000
to get good at anything and maybe it's
not true but I early in my career and
maybe even now I wanted to become a very
good software engineer right and people
always ask me hey what book did you read
what did you what what did you do to
become a good software engineer and I'm
like I wrote and read a lot of code like
just anything you can get your hands on
and there's so much more code. No, there
you can read, consume, and write. Um,
and I'm not sure if it's good advice,
but what I know is that I did not get
good at software engineering or building
building a programming, whatever you
want to call it, from like seeing
something online or reading a a blog
post or it's like just do it. Like build
everything. databases, distributed
systems, games, like every everything
you build will teach you a new skill
that you don't even know you have until
later on. Um, my GitHub is a graveyard
of projects. I just build stuff and put
it on there. It's like I want to learn
how to do um multi and forget I I tried
to build a fighting game when I was 16.
I wanted to build Street Fighter. So, I
got all the art from somewhere online. I
started to build a Street Fighter clone.
And it wasn't for any real purpose. It
was just to learn how to build a
fighting game, right? How do you make
key combos work and like how do you make
that stuff work? Um, and that pattern of
like I need to know how this thing works
has served me like to this day, right?
Like I need I need to understand how the
thing I'm doing works. How do I get this
thing to be on that thing? Um, yeah. So,
I I
love what I do and I think that has
helped me um do it more and get better
at it.
>> And then last question, if you could go
back to yourself when you were just
graduating college and entering the
industry and give yourself some advice,
what would you say?
>> Oh my god, negotiate your freaking
salary. When I got my job, I did not
know that I could even negotiate. I
would have gotten more offers. I mean,
looking back, it doesn't matter right
now, but if I was going to talk to a new
college hireer getting a job, like get
multiple offers
>> and like bump up that money, bump it up,
bump it up. Um, I watched my friends do
it and I was I was just like in shock.
Like, I'm from Barbados, I go to the
States, I get an internship, I get a
job, they give me the most money I've
ever seen in my life. And I'm like,
"Thank you. Thank you. Thank you for the
money. I have my job. To hear kids talk
about, yeah, I I said no or I said I'm
going to go check out Google first or
Facebook and get offers and I was just
like what? And that just became normal.
Like that became like the norm and it
just it blew my mind. I couldn't
rationalize what was happening. I I do
think it's definitely worthwhile doing
that. I I've seen kids do it so well.
I'm like this is so impressive. This is
just like this kid is is telling us no.
and and and I've been I've been like on
enough hiring committees now to to hire
interns and I'm watching the back and
forth between this kid and the recruiter
and I'm just like this kid's a genius
bumping up this awake. It's so amazing.
Mass respect.
>> Awesome. All right. Well, thank you so
much for your time, David. Really
appreciate it. Um is there anything that
you want to say now or maybe where can
people find you? Uh, I am available on
X, Discord, um, Blue Sky. Are those the
mains now? Are there more?
>> I mean, there's LinkedIn, but I don't
know if you use it.
>> LinkedIn. LinkedIn. Yeah, you're right.
LinkedIn.
>> It's funny. LinkedIn has become a social
network is the most bizarre thing ever.
I am on all these things.
>> Tweeting about net and AI and all kinds
of programming stuff.
>> Awesome. I'll put it in the links in the
show notes. Thanks so much, dude.
>> Awesome.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to